[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Gavin Henry and
today my guest is Brandon Matthews
Brendan is a seasoned software engineer
entrepreneur and active open- Source
contributor with over 20 years of
Industry experience he has been working
with Russ since his early days
contributing to various Rush tools and
open source projects and is the author
of two books idiomatic rust and code
like a pro in Rust both from Manning
Brandon is also the creator of coni a
popular system monitoring tool and a
longtime member of the paty software
Foundation Brendon welcome to software
engineering radio is there anything I
missed in your bio that you'd like to
add no that's pretty good nice work to
BS and your bel's pretty impressive
one's impressive enough to lay the
foundation I'd like to start with an
overview of what tic rust is so what
does this mean it's a good question so I
suppose I mean forget rust for a second
to write any software in a way that is
idiomatic is to do it such that the way
you're using it is in line with the best
practices and patterns that are
well-known Comm
used generally for whatever that
language or tooling is and a lot of that
is pretty subjective I would say right
and these things are also like context
dependent just as an example every
different company tends to have their
own ideas about how to do like coding
style and so on and you know some
companies will say like we want all our
variable names camel case and others
might prefer snake case or whatever and
often it's also just like codebase
dependent like if you're doing open-
Source stuff generally you follow
whatever pattern that project that
you're contributing to already uses and
so anyway in the case of rust rust has
its own idioms and patterns that make
sense in a rust World rust specifically
because it
introduces some new ideas about how to
do programming I would say it means
there are some new idioms and patterns
that you would not have seen in any
other programming languages unless
you've used ones that have very similar
features to what you have in Rust which
you know other languages have the
features that rust has like at least
nowadays it's not like rust is the only
language in the world that has traits or
whatever but if you're coming from say
python to rust then it's probably a
wildly different world from what you're
used to so how do you get up to speed
very quickly such that you can write
rust that make sense in a rust world I
guess and you mentioned sort of
standards and styles there within
companies is idiomatic in relation to
any language the same as a code style or
code standards that you've set or are
they different it's a good question so I
spent some time talking about this in my
book actually so one thing is defining
the difference between a pattern or a
design pattern and an idiom and
generally speaking at least the way that
I Define it is that idioms relate to
things like code formatting more like
stylistic things and example like I
already used is how do you format your
variable names to use snake case or
camel case in the case of rust rust has
like a bit of a quirky pattern or idiom
that it uses which is that generally
most like variables are snake case
whereas names of you know structures or
enums or whatever their definitions are
going to be I guess it's not camel case
but whatever is the casing where like
the first character is uppercase maybe
that is just camel case although when I
think of camel case I usually think like
the first character is lower case and in
any case and then there are like few
other ones like if you define a global
variable in Rust
then that's supposed to be all uppercase
you know separated by underscores
whatever that's called and so these
idioms like if you think about it
actually doesn't really matter how you
format your variable names in real life
right like once the code gets run
through the compiler and comes out the
other end like these things don't really
matter so in that sense it's just purely
stylistic right that's totally different
from something like design pattern which
design pattern s relate more to how you
structure the code in like more of an
architectural sense and that can affect
actual outcomes like performance and
algorithm run times and stuff probably
trivially but it can have some effect to
a certain degree especially if you're
talking about getting into like CPU
caches and stuff yeah we're going to
touch on some of the patterns that you
mentioned in your book in the next
couple sections you T touched upon
talking about what should be the right
way to do things like the cases or the
Styles and when in fact it doesn't
really matter and that's something that
I've come across myself because I've
been learning Russ for a while now and
you just have this inbuilt feeling that
you want to do it right you know what's
the right way to do it so are we bad
programmers if we don't write idiomatic
rust well this is a tricky question and
again I think this is something I talk
about in my book but the way I see it is
that you're generally writing software
for two different audiences right like
one is the computer or the compiler
wherever the execution environment for
the code and the way that computers
handle the code doesn't really matter at
all from a stylistic perspective right
and if you're working entirely by
yourself on private code in your own
little proprietary world I suppose then
this St istic stuff really doesn't
matter at all outside of your own
preferences right like you can do
whatever you want you know like you
don't even have to write your variable
names in English if you don't want to
even though English seems to be kind of
like the standard for most software code
generally when you start working on
anything that involves working with
other people collaboration then they're
like there's sort of like two layers to
the language right the first layer is
the layer that is written for the
machine or the comp ER like the actual
instructions that tell the computer what
to do that's one layer and then the
second layer is the layer that involves
how you're communicating to other people
who have to read your code how the code
works and this is where these idioms and
patterns matter because language is
essentially just a system of like
patterns and grammars and different
structures that contain words that you
know words are basically just symbols
that represent different ideas and
things and people and places and so on
and without like a sensible structure
that anyone can understand then you're
kind of just like inventing your own
language and so if everyone is speaking
their own language then nobody's talking
to anyone because nobody understands
what anyone else is saying and keep in
mind like there needs to be a certain
amount of overlap between different
dialects and so on in English for
example so people speak in different
accents and you can generally understand
what people are saying across different
accents and if you think of an accent as
analogous to like different programming
coding Styles then yeah there are
variations but the actual underlying
language like if you're speaking English
needs to be relatively in order for you
to like communicate and understand what
someone else is saying and so on you
need to follow the idiomatic English so
to speak to communicate effectively
what I'm understanding you saying there
is the fundamental underlying rust
language when other people are trying to
read what you've written you don't want
to get in the way of them trying to
understand what you're actually
suggesting the code should do so if
you're not following those idioms or
patterns then they've got to spend time
trying to break through like your
analogy of the accent to understand your
intention right not just that but like
the way that the human brain works is
that it's just constantly doing pattern
pattern matching and so when you're
looking at someone else's code the
faster you can recognize and understand
what the patterns and the structures are
and what they mean then the faster you
can understand the code and the more it
aligns with sort of the well-known well
understood idiomatic things about that
language is practices then the faster
you can get up to speed on that code and
as someone writing the code the easier
your code is for other people to
understand the more valuable it is and
as someone reading the code then the
quicker you're able to like recognize
the patterns and understand what's
happening without having to necessarily
walk through each line of code and
trying to understand what is happening
here then if you can understand what's
happening in that code very quickly
without having to go through everything
like line by line and figure out where
each bite is going and what's happening
then you save yourself a lot of time and
so a shortcut to making code easy to
write needed to understand for different
people is to follow you know stick to
well understood patterns and idioms and
so on yeah that helps me with your
analogy because you can wouldn't
necessarily be classed as a bad
programmer if it's just for yourself cuz
no one's else going to see it but as
soon as you get there then they might
just think that so what tools are out
there or in the rust ecosystem that can
help us identify things that would need
to be reworked or things that were
missing to make our code look how others
expect it to look yeah that's a good
question so nice thing about rust is
that rust makes this pretty easy and so
for rust there are two tools that are
fairly critical if you want to write
idiomatic rust one is rust format and so
that strictly handles formatting of code
like Whit space and all that basically
deciding like where to put each
character within the source file and and
then there's another tool clippy and
clippy is less about formatting and is
more about I'd say it's sort of like
halfway between design patterns and code
formatting okay and is rust format the
same as cargo format CU I've used that
so yeah when you type cargo format
that's running Russ format which is like
the name of the formatting tool and it's
fmt type isn't it I think yes so the
rust format like the binary name is rust
R Us fmt just all one word cool I've
used clippy a lot of myself as part of
ID or on the command line and one thing
I noticed the other day is it even helps
you identify new ways that things have
done so I either referenced something
read something or took a suggestion from
co-pilot whatever it was and it give me
an old way to do Rust and then clippy
picked up and said no you don't need to
do Define a future this way anymore you
just put Ayn in front of it so it must
have been pretty old yeah clippy is
pretty useful I think it can be annoying
for example if you took clippy and you
ran it with like an older rust code base
that hadn't been updated in a while then
it's going to generate a bunch of
warnings and that might be annoying it's
a bit like C or C++ compiler warnings
and I think not so much anymore but I
remember you know back in the day maybe
like 20 years ago it wasn't unusual at
least in open source world to have these
projects where when you compile them the
compiler would just spit out like
hundreds maybe even thousands of
warnings and I think it was pretty
common for people to just like some
people Leed to just kind of ignore all
those warnings and then I think more
recently the culture kind of changed
where people were like well if compiler
is making this warning maybe I should
address it even if the code works and
compiles maybe we should just fix that
warning and so at least anecdotally what
I've notic is that most projects at
least in like C and C++ world don't have
like tons of warnings and so clippy is
sort of like that compiler warnings
except it's like at least like CN Plus+
compiler warnings generally relate more
to like the machine interpretation of
the code whereas clippy is somewhere on
the edge of like some aspects of it or
like have to do with how the code
actually affects the end result the
machine interpretation of it and some
aspects relate to just more like
stylistic and structural aspects of like
how you're writing your code so to close
off our introduction both rust format or
running on the command line cargo space
fmt format can help enforce things and
clippy you can reach for which is Cargo
space clippy as well I think yeah just
cargo clippy and that will help identify
at least get you on the path of getting
into a diomatic rust and Community
expects I think if you use these tools
they get you like 90 Plus percent of the
way there and it's actually really easy
to use these tools nowadays because if
you set up like your ID vs code or
whatever and you use the rust analyzer
extension then I think for the most part
it just turns these on by default for
you and then you can dial it up if you
want and make it basically like increase
the level of clippy and rust format
enforcement by tweaking their configs
like for example if you're using
something like vs code generally I think
by default with the rust analyzer
extension when you save your code and
you have like the format and on Save
where you have like the compiler stuff
set up then I think the command it runs
by default to check your code is Cargo
check but you can go into the settings
and just change that from cargo check to
Cargo clippy and now instead of just
running the compiler normally on your
code to check if it compiles it'll
actually run clippy which will not only
check if it compiles but also check all
your compliance with like clippy's set
of rules and so now in your IDE you have
not only like the compiler errors and
whatnot but also the clippy output
that's the first thing that I do on jet
brains rust Rover and a new one I
switched to called Zed but because I'm
in the ffi forign function interface
between C and rust I have to switch off
a lot of the clippy stuff because it's
mainly for rust whereas bring in some C
stuff it does a lot of lower case things
that clippy goes no you shouldn't be
doing that so you've got to switch off
yeah generally I think for most projects
maybe early on you can start using clip
e and rust format and you just kind of
stick with the defaults but in practice
it'll probably reach a point where you
have to go in and tweak the
configuration either to like you know on
this file ignore this check or whatever
or just you know adjust it to whatever
your preferences are but certainly for
like a pure rust project
where you're not doing anything too
unusual I would say then the defaults
should be pretty good I'd like to now
move us on to our sort of main section
spend the next 15 minutes or so talking
about the main items in your book I
would say generics and traits because
you state they are the main building
blocks for idiomatic rust so shall we
explore both sure so I'll start with
generics what are generics good question
so without trying to like look it up on
Wikipedia yeah just a oneliner got about
seven bullet points per generics and
trait so a oneliner would be good first
of all generics are not you know unique
or NE rust it's an idea that exists
around for a while but the general
concept is that you have some kind of
structure and you want to be able to
build a structure in a quote generic
sense such that that's structure can
operate on different kinds of underlying
data so you can create an instance
instantiate an instance of your
structure and you can put you can have
an integer as its internal data or you
can have a string or you can have some
other structure inside that and these
generic structures can then be applied
you know you can reuse the same
structure for bunch of different kinds
of data so like the classic example of
this I suppose in Rust would be like you
have a vector which is essentially just
like a list of things and or an array
and you might want to store a string or
an integer or you know some other
structure within your vector and that
Vector is generic in the sense that it
can hold any different kind of thing
provided all of those items within that
sequence are of the same type generics
generally only matter in languages that
are statically typed because you have to
know what the types are ahead of time I
would say how does rust provide them is
it because of its strong types or yeah
so rust is very strict in terms of its
typing discipline so generally speaking
all types need to be known at compile
time you know that's totally different
from any sort of dynamically typed
language where you don't have to think
about types when you're writing the code
and the
environment we'll figure out types at
runtime problem with Dynamic typing is
of course like things can blow up at
runtime if you don't handle all the
cases that you need to handle when your
code is executing and gets data that is
not what you expect and then you know if
you're doing any sort of static typing
you have to handle all of the cases at
compile time the advantage of that is
that you don't have type errors at
runtime the disadvantage is that you
have like more work or higher cognitive
load at compile time when you're writing
the code in order to think about
different types and so on you gave us an
example where a vector holds all the
same type and a structure or generic we
might want to hold different things
would that be a good case of when we
know we should reach for generics and
we've got this modeled up sort of
different types of data is that correct
yeah so I think generally the default
use case for generics is that you want
to make something that some structure
that holds other things and you don't
necessarily know what the other things
are that you want to hold right this is
a little different like if you think
about like kind of two main types of
structures right one is where you
already know all the things that are in
the structure like it's going to hold
this count and it's going to hold this
string which is a name of a thing and it
has this other thing and so on right
that's sort of like the not generic
structure it's just it's always this
well-known thing and it's like a fixed
shape the other kind of structure is
something where you're defining you know
you're like architecting a data
structure that has certain properties
but you don't know what is going to be
inside that data structure or you know
maybe you do know but you want to have
it hold something you know hold a string
in some cases and hold an integer in
other cases in which case you want to
use generics or you may just want to
build a structure and use generics so
that perhaps in the future you can apply
that structure to like other problems or
other data types what would the pros and
cons of starting out with a generic
structure so you could take a string and
do something if it's a string or do
something different with an integer
versus just going for a normal structure
at a basic level the advantage using
generics is again like you can increase
code reuse so rather than having to
write a vector for Strings and a vector
for integers and a vector for whatever
you just have one vector and you can
make it generic for you know most types
that satisfy whatever the requirements
are to be in that structure so that's
nice but the main tradeoff like the
reason why generics might kind of suck
in some cases is that well there are two
problems they introduce more complexity
generally when comes to writing the code
like it's it's harder to write
structures for generic data types for
any kind of complicated cases right and
when you start to introduce generics you
end up having to start adding in more
and more other abstractions to sort of
work around the fact that you've added
this new layer of complexity so that's a
disadvantage another disadvantage to
generics is just that in a language like
rust it's it's very very hard to do
certain things generically in practice
right like yes you can make a structure
that holds both string and strings and
integers but there are certain
operations that just can't be done
generically for example you know you can
sum two integers but like you can't
really sum two strings that's just I
mean you you could Define your own
definition for what it means to sum two
strings but like strictly speaking
there's no such thing as summing strings
right like they're not numbers they
can't be added to each other and so if
you wanted to have a structure and like
it had like a summing operation in it
you're going to have to handle those
special cases somehow in your code so
like even when you do these generic
things you might often end up having to
actually like add special cases where
they're strictly not generic so like you
know you have a structure and if there's
an integer in there then everything's
fine but then in the special case we're
like oh I have a string now I have to do
something different and so it's a little
funny in that sense because you strictly
speaking you're adding more comp a lot
of more complexity by using generics and
so you have to balance that trade-off do
you want it to
do you want to have this like additional
flexibility with the downside of having
more complexity or do you want to just
have like a very basic structure and
just make sure everything is known
without any generics and then when you
don't use generics a lot of things do
become much easier generally when it
comes to writing the code which is
something you would see very quickly if
you use rust I guess does rust figure
out what the types are going to be of
the generic structure at compile time or
does it do some of it at runtime or is
it well generally yeah it's all going to
be happening at compile time but like
the Russ language itself doesn't do any
of that at runtime for the most part
with a couple of minor exceptions but if
you wanted though you could introduce
like your own layer of dynamic typing
sort of at runtime within your own code
you know there are also like crates that
effectively do this and the way that you
do that is that you have generic
containers that wrap some other type of
data and so you're you know you
introduce like a new layer of
abstraction or interaction in between
your data type yeah no I didn't want to
do it I was just interested where it
looks everything how do generics compare
to other languages the rust version
compared to others and then I'll move us
on to traits because we've got quite a
bit still to go over so I would say rust
generics are very similar to what you
would find in say C++ templates but
they're a little different overall from
anything else mainly because unlike a
language like C++ C++ has classes and
Russ doesn't have a concept of classes
it instead uses traits which you know
talk about but you know off top of my
head I can't really think of like
languages that are really super similar
to rust in terms of how it handles
generics and you know C++ is fairly
strict relatively strict and it's like
templates is what would be the
equivalent in C++ and then languages
like Java for example have generics but
Java's generics I think are like a
little more flexible than like a C++ and
their Java is a bit easier to use
generally which do you think influenced
rust the most out of what you've seen in
your life I think personally at least
with regard to the generics in Rust I
would say it's a combination of like
multiple languages I think C++ is a big
influence we'll come back to that we'll
say C++ so the other big part you said
there that rust doesn't have classes it
has traits so what are traits or what is
a trait and how does rust provide them
with a nice example so we can understand
that would be perfect so traits are a
way of describing behaviors or features
that apply to different types of data
right so a trait itself is strictly a
definition
of some behavior and when I say Behavior
I mean like generally a trait it's like
some method or a set of methods that
apply to some type so a trait itself is
not an implementation of anything it's
just like an interface or description in
fact interface is the word used for
traits in some other languages like
Scala for example and so your interface
just describes how you can interact with
the data type and the trait is sort of
like a generic useful language that you
can use to say this object has these
features essentially yeah I understand
it as a shared Behavior between types is
what I always think when I read the word
trait and then I think of when you put a
derive display or something like that on
something I think that was a trait I'm
not sure that's why I've got an expert
on so the thing with traits is that you
need to implement them for any given
structure or type right so if you define
your own structure or an enum or
something and you want it to have
certain behaviors then you need to
implement that trait so like let's use a
an example of a trait that's like
something you would very commonly
Implement for things in Rust and that
would be the Clone trait now clone is
generic enough that you don't actually
have to write the implementation you
don't have to do like imple clone for
your structure you can derive it using a
macro and that works because most of the
basic types in Rust have these traits
implemented right so like a string has a
clone implemented already integers
already have a clone and and so on and
so forth so if your structure is made up
of all these basic types that already
have a tradeit implemented then you can
just automatically derive a clone
implementation for your type using a
macro because all the macro has do is
just call clone for all of the types
contained within your type and so it's
relatively easy to just automatically
derive those very generic traits but for
anything more complicated than that then
you're going to have to like write the
actual implementation manually for
whatever it is or you know if you want
to get fancy you can actually just write
those derived macros yourself for like
if you want to make a crate and Define
some trait and make it so other people
can just say derive this trait for any
type then you can create your own macro
and do that thanks so I'm going to move
us on to the patterns part in your book
for the last bit of the show and then
anti patterns but just to summarize
traits there and some terminology we
introduced for those that aren't
familiar we Implement things on a type
so this is my understanding so pull it
apart the Mac Ros are a way to inject
some other code above something or in
Rust to say put this bit of rust code
here and the copy trait allows you to
deal with the ownership of a variable
that is a string or something so you can
copy that string to another owner rather
than borrow or fetch and then you said
traits are similar to interfaces in
other languages or is that all just
rubbish that's mostly right except I
should point out that in Rust cloning C
copy mean different things it's like a
subtle difference there and usually when
people say copy in Rust what they mean
is clone copy has like its own separate
nuanced definition which strictly means
at least we're talking about the copy
trait copy strictly means that you can
duplicate to objects by making a a
literal bite copy right so an example of
like something that you can copy is an
integer right you have one integer you
want to make another copy of it you can
l just copy the bytes straight over but
that doesn't work for a lot of objects
because internally their representation
might include
pointers and you can't just copy a
pointer necessarily I mean unless that's
your intent but usually what you have to
do is you have to copy the actual
contents of what that pointer is
pointing to and then move it over and so
you can't do a you know a direct bite
copy and so rust disambiguates that by
using the word clone instead which
implies that you just want to make a new
copy of that object with the same
contents but it's not strictly you know
like you can't just copy the pointer and
have it point to the old data you need
to have a a new copy of that internal
data you might call it a deep copy I
guess I understand and could you think
of a trait like a base class and an
object oriented language so if you
inherit from That Base Class you've got
the shared Behavior or is that the wrong
way to think about it yeah it's
difficult to draw direct analogies
between traits and classes because I
think if you try to do that you're just
confusing yourself yeah just alar in the
new way yeah I think it's just better to
say like it's not the same as classes
and just learn traits and forget about
classes cool so the next section is is
patterns and then anti-patterns after
that I've pulled out six patterns in
your book but I don't think we're going
to have time to go over them those so if
I list these six and you want to pick
your three favorites that you see more
often than not would that work sure
we've got macro pattern Builder pattern
fluent interface Observer commands and U
type I've seen you type around but I've
not looked into it so if we could do
that one that would be good and then
another two that you think would be good
for the listeners yeah so I think
probably the ones that you might see
most often or maybe another way i' put
it is like patterns that you would get
the most benefit toolings that you get
the most benefit out of properly
understanding is probably yeah the top
two or the Builder pattern is very
useful and once you get into using that
it's like hard to stop using it fluent
interfaces are also very useful you will
if you're not familiar with them you
haven't encountered them before then
you'll very quickly like see those used
elsewhere and again once you like get
into using them then it's it's hard not
to use them because they're you know
they're fun to use and it's a nice
abstraction and you know I wouldn't
describe macros as like a whole pattern
but learning to use some of the basic
macro patterns is super valuable because
you know there's sort of like two levels
of writing software the beginner level
is you go and you you know you write you
actually write the code out like you
type it out or you copy it from chat gbt
or whatever right yeah that's me that's
level one and then level two is that you
rather than writing code you get to the
point where like you're writing code to
write the code code generators yeah
right essentially macros right or rather
macros are are one way to do that and in
Russ there are two different types of
macros there are declarative macros
which is kind of like the I don't want
to say easy but maybe like less
complicated way of doing macros and then
the other type of macro is a procedural
macro and in Rust a proc cedal macro is
where you essentially write rust code
that generates rust code by directly
manipulating the term in Rust is well
this is not rust specific but the term
is abstract syntax tree a and that's
just a representation or like a data
structure representation of the syntax
of the source code that you can you know
alter programmatically but you can also
just write code that generates source
code like strings and essentially spit
that out of your ma macro you don't have
to use macros but every once in a while
you'll come upon a case where it's like
well it would be great if I could do
this without just like copying and
pasting a bunch of code or maybe writing
a python script that spits out my code
or things that I've done in the past and
aren't really the worst thing in the
world are for example like you might
have a yaml file that contains a bunch
of data and then you write like a python
script with like ginger Tu template or
something and you like read in the yaml
and then feed that into your template
plate that spits out say rust code or
something else that's not really the
worst thing in the world but to like a
level beyond that is getting into
learning using rust macros directly
which you don't have to do but if you
want to be in like a 100% pure rust
world then that would be though so
that's using rust to generate rust code
before it gets compiled yeah that's the
other thing about macros is they they
execute before the code is actually fed
into the compiler so it's a step before
compilation it's basically a step after
you write the code and before it gets
compiled yeah like a pre-processor in C
is that it's similar to pre-processors
in C but you can't really compare it
directly to that because C
pre-processors are pretty naive I would
say they let you do things that you
probably shouldn't do and they don't
properly handle like typing and so on
and so forth so we would reach for
macros when we can't be bothered typing
anymore or we want some extra stuff
created when you can't be bothered
typing or if you're like typing out the
exact same structure or or you know code
or boiler plate over and over again then
you might want to be like well I could
just write a macro for this and is that
normally found in a a library that you'd
publish to we mentioned a create and
things before this which is crates. iio
and a way to share code between rust
programs so correct yeah crates are just
rust packages that it could be a library
or a program
and would you use macros in a binary
project or a library project or a create
or just whatever it makes sense oh well
you can use them in all of the above but
if you want to write a macro as part of
a library you can absolutely do that so
you can create a crate that exports some
macro and you know reuse that elsewhere
that's a pretty common thing in Rust and
you mentioned fluent in interface
pattern would be something that we'd see
quite a lot yes so probably a good
example of this in Russ that is
essentially part of the core language
would be iterators which well you can
use iterators in multiple ways but one
way is to use them using the fluent
pattern where you essentially like chain
a set of operations together which would
be like you know map and filter and
whatever and you can stack these
operations and operate on some sequence
of items by breaking your operations
down into like distinct you know
generally like functions that apply some
operation or whatever to the data and
then return some result that would be
like pretty common way to interact in
Rust that way so are we thinking of
interface like we spoke about a trait or
is it do we not think about it like that
is it just an interface to a function so
no it's not similar tra you might use
traits within your implementation of
that interface but generally speaking
like if you're building a fluent
interface it's going to be made up of
methods that you write as part of a
structure but the method itself returns
something where you can then apply you
know the next operation or or there's
another method in that thing that is
returned that you can then apply some
operation too that makes sense yeah so
is that kind of like functional
programming where everything function
and you can turn that and act on it or
so when I was talking about iterators
and their fluent interface that is the
way that you use that with erators that
would be a good example of like a
functional pattern but fluent interfaces
don't necessarily have to be functional
in the sense that with iterators you're
usually passing a function as the
argument into you know whatever step
you're applying to the the items in the
sequence or whatever but your fluent
interface doesn't have to take functions
as parameters it could be fairly
non-functional and still be a fluent
interface I suppose that makes sense I
mean I've seen that in Rust code I've
seen it in other languages where you
kind of passing a closure to the
function to go and do something once
it's found something I should just
Define that strictly speaking like a
fluent interface is just an interface
that uses method chaining right so you
chain multiple method calls together
effectively and the thing that you
return from the first method call has to
be an object generally like you might
have a method call that's like terminal
in the sense that like if you call this
that ends the chain basically but
generally what the fluid interface
returns is some object that has more
calls that you can make and you you know
chain them together basically okay well
we've only managed to do two out of the
six there so I'll put a link into the
book so people can dig in deeper if they
like but there are two common ones that
we would see to move you from level one
rust to being Elite I suppose so we've
got patterns we discussed two of six
that was macros and Float interface you
spoke about Builder Observer command and
U type but we'll leave those for now and
you also speak which I like that you
have this in your book which is why I
want to talk about it for the last bit
of the show anti patterns so we've come
along we're into rust we've reached for
cargo forat we've reached for clippy
we're getting all the help that the
Fantastic rust ecosystem gives us
because it's vetted and checked to
compile times we get all this lovely
lovely things but we need to think about
the or code smells or stuff that we see
around to keep an eye out for so is that
what you define an antipattern yeah so
anti- patterns are things you shouldn't
do and I suppose in a perfectly designed
language there would be no anti-
patterns because you wouldn't be allowed
to do anything you shouldn't do but in
practice that's pretty hard but if the
compiler lets you do it then it can't be
bot well yeah most of the time right
like the best example of this in Rust is
of course the unsafe keyword and as the
name implies it's sort of like this
escape hatch that lets you get around
rusts strict rules about how you handle
memory and so on yeah I use that every
day so generally I would call like
unsafe and anti- pattern but it's you
know it's not very black and white right
there are still no matter what going to
be certain cases where you have no
choice but to use this thing and you
know some of the rust Pur might say like
well I don't want to use any code that
uses unsafe because I don't want my code
to be unsafe and I'm not saying that if
that's your philosophy that's fine but I
think the word unsafe you know I think
like when the Russ language designers
chose the term unsafe that was maybe not
the best word because you can still do
things that are safe but require unsafe
code and you can see examples of this
just by looking through the rust
standard Library where there are certain
operations that are totally safe but
they still require unsafe code because
you just can't do them in under rust set
of rules without having them happen with
an unsafe code an unsafe marks a block
or a function sorry you use the keyword
unsafe one word to Mark a block of code
or a function to say if you see a
pointer or anything that is normally
banned I know what I'm doing so maybe it
should actually be called I know what
I'm doing yeah something like that yeah
yeah you're basically on the right track
it's basically like you're telling the
compiler I want you to temporarily
suspend your strict rules I want you to
set the borrow checker on vacation for a
moment while I move this data around or
like you know move these pointers around
or something because I just have to do
this to make my code work right like it
just has to be done and there's no other
way due to the limitations of computers
basically you know sometimes you just
have to do that a good example of like
where you might have to write unsafe
code that is generally perfectly safe
would be like certain types of system
calls for example yeah using C libraries
yeah C libraries you know the reality of
computers and software and operating
systems is that no matter what you're
going to have to interact with the
outside world to do anything useful
right do any kind of IO and in order to
do those things you're going to have to
make call like do some type of function
call or whatever that is strictly
speaking unsafe in Russ terms and
there's just no other way to do it right
yeah because it can't reason about the
memory or the ownership or anything like
that so right right exactly one that
jumped out as a beginner although I've
written a lot of rust code now it's
still level one or level two that
surprised me in your book was where you
said an antipattern would be seeing the
unwrap keyword everywhere which if you
could just Define what unwrap does and
then why if you see it in a program
Everywhere You class that as bad that
would be great yeah so calling unwrap a
any pattern might be controversial
because unwrap in a way it's a bit like
unsafe right you're telling the compiler
or or whatever that like I know better
than you I know that this call is not
going to fail so I don't need to check
it right and to explain what unrap is
for anyone that doesn't know there are
certain structures which are designed to
like hold something that may or may not
exist right like the two best examples
of this are result and option which when
you write rust you end up using a lot so
in the case of an option an option it's
a structure that holds something that
either is or isn't I guess it's just
binary right so you know you might have
a a string and you either have the
string or you don't and so if you have a
string then you know you can just get
the string from the option if you don't
have the string then the option contains
a type called nun right and an option is
just an e num and it just contains two
possible things one being some is what
it is like s right like something and
then none and with an option it takes a
certain amount of boiler plate to like
always handle both cases right so in in
your code you know you might want to
occasionally just like skip handling
both the cases in particular if you know
for sure that it's not going to contain
none and it doesn't matter right so an
example this might be you have some code
where you construct that option and you
put something into it immediately and
then on the next line of code you don't
actually need to like go through the
process of like checking is it none do
you know handle like that's an error or
something like you don't really need to
go through that because you you already
know that option is always going to
contain something because you literally
just put something in there on the
previous line of code so you could just
call unwrap and unwrap just Returns what
that option or result or whatever
contains while like skipping the whole
bit about like handling the like error
or noncase and that's fine but if you
start to use that in contexts where you
should be checking if your option or
result actually holds the thing that you
want then now your code is going to blow
up at runtime so if you think of like
unwrap is this escape hatch that lets
you get around having to handle the like
the nunc case or the error case in the
case of a result so none in case of
option and error in the case of result
then I would say it's a little bit lazy
right especially if you're using that
where you shouldn't use it and it's very
easy to do and I'll try and think of
another example as well and where I've
used it is say for example I'm trying to
load a TLS certificate on a command line
tool for example at startup if you just
used unwrap and didn't say to the user
that's loading it oh I can't find this
would you like to create one or
something like that right if you're
deploying the binary it just might never
start you know and you're not handling
that situation slickly you're just kind
of say oh well I don't care if this
crashes but then in the same context you
might not care if it crashes because
it's just something you've written you
know for yourself you're always running
it it's all super contextual you got to
ask yourself like does it matter but I
do make one suggestion in the book which
is that in cases where you're using
unwrap because you're being lazy which
is not a bad thing necessarily my
suggestion is that instead of using
unwrap you use expect which is it's
essentially the same thing as unwrap but
with one difference which is that you
can put a message in so it's kind of
like using assert for example right like
you already are very confident that this
thing is what it should be so on the the
exceptional case where it's not what it
should be then now you can just type a
little error message and the nice thing
about using expect is then if you're
your program blows up then it will at
least give you an indication of why it
blew up provided your you know your
message is helpful so that's one
suggestion but also if you're using
unwrap without really understanding why
you're using it if you think about it or
even expect for that matter it's just
like oh this is just how you get the
value out of an option if that's how you
think about it then you're that's
definitely an anti pattern like you
definitely need to understand like what
is the correct way to use that in what
context when I first started I just
thought unwrap was how you write rust
and everything had unwrap on it every
example I've ever seen on any any
website or book it was unrap and then
yeah I learned more and then I went to
expect if it was someone using the
program like myself and I was like what
just unwrapped and why did this crash
and then oh you expect because you can
say this is why it did this so I suppose
it's a journey yeah it is okay let's
finish off this section cuz I can't
believe we're almost done already are
there any favorites anti patterns of
yours that we should watch out for or
code smells that you often see in
programs that we should make people
aware of that's a tough question I mean
I think like unwrap is a good one unsafe
is another good one if you see people
using those a lot in normal rust code
then that indicates that whoever is
writing that code either doesn't really
have a good understanding of rust and
how to use it or you know they're being
like just very lazy about the way they
rate rust those are good ones I think
Beyond those there aren't really a lot
of great major Annie patterns in Rust I
would say because it's so strict about
how you do things like it starts starts
to all get I guess very like stylistic
and wishy-washy but an example though I
would say is that like some people in
the rust world really don't like for
example using clone too often right yeah
I've got some notes here and clone is in
there yeah people sometimes again it's
sort of like the unwrap or unsafe like
people who are new to rust sometimes
will start to use clone too often
because again it gives you a way to sort
of get around rust's strictness like if
you're trying to pass an object around
and you want to use references then
handling references means you have to
deal with the borrow Checker and that
makes things a little more tricky in
Rust and so one easy way to get around
that is you just make a copy right like
you clone your thing like a string that
you're passing around or whatever and
that's not necessarily bad but you know
like Russ purus would frown upon that
because now you're adding this
additional like overhead and increasing
your memory usage and wasting a bit of
time like allocating more memory and so
on and more importantly it's not
idiomatic it so personally I think like
clone is nitpicking on clone is kind of
a bad example because it's just so
context dependent and it's sort of like
sliding scale of like how strict do you
want to be sometimes there are cases
where it's just going to be way easier
to just clone this just make a copy of
it right you can take this even farther
to getting into the idea of making all
data structures immutable and when you
do that you always make copies of things
right because you don't modify memory so
if you want to change something you have
to copy it anyway yeah that's what they
do in elix arm and Airline right and so
you can't be super rigid about these
because at the end of the day it's like
rust is just a tool and you can use it
in a lot of different ways and it's not
necessarily right or wrong to do a
specific thing it's all just very
context dependent and it's also I think
answering whether or not you should do
one of these things is hard when you
don't have a lot of experience using
these but over time like the more you
use them you start to get a sense of
like does it make sense to actually use
clone here but you just have to practice
and write code and you start to learn
and get a sense for it I think the first
thing personally as a beginner is just
getting it to compile and shut up all
the tools that are really helpful yeah
yeah okay well I want to sneak in one
last question if we've got time and then
wrap up so I think I asked you this on
our sound check do you have a good list
or a rust project that we could read or
look at on any open source thing that
has a lot of what we've discussed you
know your go-to one I say go and look at
this yeah well the default answer to
this is actually just the rust standard
library and the nice thing about rust's
built-in documentation tool which is
called rust do is that when it generates
the docs it gives you a link to the
source code for everything so like one
of the most common data structures that
you would use in Rust whenever you're
using rust is the vet like vector and so
you know if you want like very quick
introduction to looking at idiomatic
rust code then I would just like Google
the Rust VEC docs and open them up and
just start clicking on the little Source
link on the different methods and see
what's going on inside the rust code
excellent I'll put the link to that in
the show notes okay I'm really glad we
did the show and I hope it helps others
understand what idiomatic rust means I
certainly learn a lot was there anything
we missed that you'd like to mention
before we finish off no not really I
hope people enjoy and we'll link to your
book so everything we didn't get a
chance to speak about is covered in your
brilliant book and if people want to get
in touch or reach out to ask you
something what's the best way to do that
email or I mean if you Google my name
with GitHub then you can find my get up
account and you know I don't know email
is probably the best way generally
Brandon thank you for coming on the show
it's been a real pleasure this is Gavin
Henry for software engineering radio
thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at
[Music]
slack Channel at seo. slack.com you can
also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening